After 400 years, the three-body civilization will arrive.
明明400年后三体人才到
Before then
在那之前
live happily.
开开心心活着
Live on your own terms.
照自己想法活着
This is a responsibility you have to yourself.
这才是对自己负责啊
These two big living people can't stand it.
这俩大活人都看不住
Nothing can happen to him or Zhuang Yan.
他和庄颜谁都不能出事儿
Thank you Mr. Luo Ji.
谢谢您罗辑先生
I will remember the starry sky tonight.
我会记得今晚的星空
Von Neumann
冯・诺伊曼
Frederick Tyler's Wall Breaker.
弗里德里克・泰勒的破壁人
The B436 project experiment has come a long way.
B436项目实验已经走得很远
I advise you
我劝你
Enough is enough.
适可而止
We just want to observe the energy redundancy after the ball lightning attack.
我们只是要观察球闪攻击后的能量冗余
It's completely safe.
完全可以
Who's in charge here?
这儿到底谁说了算
Mr. Tyler.
泰勒先生
I
我
am your wall breaker.
是您的破壁人
Call security.
叫警卫
Get him out of here.
把他赶出去
Monitor the ball lightning recovery progress.
监测球闪回收进度
Remote sensors show that Ghost 1 has locked the position of the ball lightning.
远程显示幽灵1号已锁定球闪位置
The ball lightning was captured successfully.
球闪捕获成功
The recycling program is working fine.
回收程序运行正常
Thank you sir.
谢谢您先生
I won't take long.
不会用太长时间的
You are planning to create a
您打算建立一支
space army armed with ball lightning.
以球状闪电为武器的太空军队
Am I right?
对吗
Pity
可惜
No one survived.
里面没有活人
Are you crazy?
你疯了吗
How could there be people on the target ship?
标靶飞船上怎么会有人
Troubleshoot the tracks.
排查轨道
Start the return journey.
开始返程
Acknowledged.
收到
Thanks.
谢谢
At the last experiment on the ground
上次的地面实验
The real target
真正的标靶
wasn't that black obelisk
不是那块黑色方碑
despite its beauty.
虽然它很漂亮
However, you don't care.
但您根本不在乎
I noticed
我注意到
Your sight is always intentional and unintentional.
您的视线总是有意无意地
observing those sheep.
扫过那些羊
Certainly.
当然
Yes.
是的
They are everywhere.
它们到处都是
But you're actually paying attention to their behavior.
但您其实在留意它们的习性
You see that they are everywhere in the desert.
好让这些在荒漠草原到处都是的
You know nothing about them except that they eat
除了吃一无所知的脊椎动物
and are active near the target area.
留在靶区附近活动
Leave them be.
别管了
This is an advanced laboratory.
先进实验室
Then under your ingenious arrangement
然后在您的巧妙安排下
had them struck by ball lightning with a modified spectrum.
被修改频谱后的球状闪电击中
In the quantum state
以量子态的形式
they could pass through walls.
穿墙越壁
Like the real accident
像个真正的意外那样
they appeared in the target area
出现在靶区
So the sheep
所以那只羊
Or
或者说
the quantum sheep being attracted by the residual magnetic field
那只被残余磁场吸引的量子羊
is your real goal.
才是您真正的目标
And that expensive black brick
而那个耗资巨大的黑色砖块
And your anger at Dr. Elena.
还有您对埃琳娜博士的怒火
you only hold me back.
就只能来拖我的后腿
It's just an act for your scheme.
只是您计谋的装饰品而已
Your have a rich imagination
你的想象力很丰富
but, my enemy is your lord,
但我的敌人是你们的主
not a sheep.
不是一只羊
Of course.
那是当然
So you visited Dr. Ding Yi again.
所以您又拜访了丁仪博士
Elena is too young
埃琳娜太年轻
and lacks experience in space operations.
缺少太空作业的经验
I still hope
我还是希望
you can lead my experiment.
你能做我的实验主导人
But you don't care about Ding Yi's reply
但您根本不在乎丁仪的答复
What you want to inquire about
您想打探的
is the B436 experiment.
是B436实验里
Secret Records on Spectrum
关于频谱的秘密记录
and about
和那个
the experiments many years ago
多年前的实验里
where a woman was declared dead.
被宣布死亡的女人
Start recording.
开始记录
7 o'clock sharp.
早上7点整
Instrument calibration complete.
仪器校准完成
please confirm.
请确认
Who is speaking?
谁在说话
You won't answer the idiot bogg's question.
您不会回答蠢货博格的问题
It doesn't matter whos voice that is.
那声音是谁并不重要
How she "died" matters.
她怎么“死”的才重要
It's almost time.
时间差不多了
Allow me to summarize your thinking.
请允许我总结一下您的思路
Firstly
首先
The sheep get hit outside target area.
羊在靶区外被击中
Their ear tags are miles away.
耳标却在数里之外
You are satisfied with the result.
这个结果您很满意
You believe that as long as the spectrum modulation of the ball lightning is correct
可见只要球闪的频谱调制准确
organisms are not only in a quantum state
生物体不仅可以被精准打击
they are also invisible to the naked eye
还会以肉眼不可见的量子态
and survive for a while
存活一段时间
and the handwriting that appeared after the woman's death proves that.
而那个女人死后才出现的字迹则证明
Human beings can not only be quantized
人类不仅可以被量子化
they are also likely to retain self-awareness.
还极有可能保留自我意识
Even to some extent
甚至一定程度上
impact our macrocosm.
影响我们的宏观世界
You abandoned morality to defeat the trisolarins.
您为了战胜三体而抛弃道德
This is not easy.
这很不容易
I express my sincere admiration.
我表示由衷的钦佩
But, I should remind you
但也要提醒您
this
这
is murder.
是在谋杀
War is a kind of murder.
战争本来就是一种杀戮
No.
不
I mean kill your own kind.
我是说杀您的同类
I didn't kill anyone.
我没杀过人
You will kill soon.
您很快就会杀人了
Alert.
警报
The base system is paralyzed.
基地系统瘫痪
Ball lightning recovery procedure tampered with.
球状闪电回收程序被篡改
Please troubleshoot immediately.
请立即排查故障
Our communication system with the outside world has also been interrupted.
我们与外界的通讯系统也中断了
Right..
对了
Now that the spectrum of the ball lightning
现在球闪的频谱
has been precisely matched with the human body.
已经和人体精准匹配
This spectrum..
频谱
What is this?
这是什么东西啊
This is a masterpiece just for you.
这是专门为您完成的杰作
Recycling process is automatic.
回收程序是自动操作的
Stop panicing.
慌什么
Restart the system.
重启系统
Contact PDC immediately.
马上和PDC联络
Ok Mr. Tyler.
好的泰勒先生
Don't worry.
不用急
Four centuries is not long.
四个世纪并不漫长
For human history
在人类史上
it's quite soon.
说很快也不为过
In the morning of the doomsday war
到了末日之战的清晨
you can imagine
您可以想象一下
Your average space soldier wakes up early
一个普通的太空军早早起床
and hide a yellowed photo in a battle suit.
把一张泛黄的照片藏在战斗服里
This is the decisive battle that
这场决战
he has been waiting for nearly a hundred years for.
他已经等待了近百年
Additional load released.
附加载荷已释放
time leads a path
铅色的时光之路
Limit speed increased by 63.16%
极限航速提升63.16%
that finally comes to an end.
终于到了尽头
The night sky is gradually lit up by battleships.
夜空逐渐被战舰点亮
Intuition tells him
直觉告诉他
the battle begins.
战斗开始了
Control center please answer.
控制中心请回答
Ghost 1.
幽灵1号
Moving towards the ladder
正朝天梯方向移动
Please answer.
收到请回答
Call Experiment Center.
呼叫实验中心
Ghost 1 has deviated 4 kilometers.
幽灵1号已偏航4公里
Can you hear?
能听到吗
He took off in a battleship
他驾驶着战舰起飞
In front of you is where all the soldiers meet
面前是所有军人相聚的地方
fire and blood
火焰和血光
will shine here
将在这里闪耀
he swears by it.
他以此为誓
His child is waiting for him.
他的孩子在等他
Long hibernation caused him to miss his parents' funeral
漫长的冬眠令他错过了父母的葬礼
He doesn't want to miss his daughter's.
他不想再错过女儿的
Target acceleration too high
目标加速度过大
It is recommended to suspend the docking order.
建议暂缓对接指令
Ignore suggestion.
忽略建议
Suddenly
突然
A beam of light hits his battleship.
一束光击中了他的战舰
Dock fit 43%
对接契合度43%
Unable to complete docking.
无法完成对接
The last thing he sees
他最后看到的
are countless blue suns.
是无数个蓝色的太阳
You call it
您称之为
ball lightning.
球状闪电
Dock fit 57%
对接契合度57%
His last thoughts
他最后想到的
Dock fit 72%
对接契合度72%
Did my comrades attack me?
是战友袭击了自己吗
Can he return to his daughter?
他还能回到女儿身边吗
Dock fit 93%
对接契合度93%
Dock fit 100%
对接契合度100%
Docking completed
对接完成
But these questions
但这些问题
won't get an answer.
都不会获得回答了
And then..
他他们
Cabin damage.
舱体受损
Countless flesh and blood bodies instantly became human ghosts in the quantum state.
无数血肉之躯瞬间成为了量子态的人类幽灵
Please fix it ASAP.
请尽快修复
Give up docking.
放弃对接
Measure the speed of the target ship.
测算目标飞船的速度
Now..
现在
they are real heroes.
他们是真的英雄了
They are finally
他们终于
invincible.
不可战胜了
Restart to complete the restoration of some system modules.
重启完成 部分系统模块恢复
Delayed data just received.
刚收到的延迟数据
Backup catcher is artificially activated.
备用捕捉器被人为启动
yes.
是
Dr. Elena.
埃琳娜博士
She is on it.
是她在驾驶
flying to the ball lightning.
球闪现在什么位置
About to enter the track where the ladder is located.
即将进入天梯所在的轨道
Send a message to the flight control center.
快给飞控中心发消息
No, the communication module is still loading.
不行通讯模块还在加载
Progress seems to be stuck.
进度好像动不了
What have you done?
你都做了什么
I did what you wanted.
做了您想做的
Create communication window.
建立通讯窗口
Contact Elena.
联系埃琳娜
What's going on?
到底什么情况
Possibly trying to crash the runaway ship #1 back into orbit
可能是想把失控的1号船撞回轨道
but we can't do it remotely.
但我们没法远程操作
Can't connect.
没法连线
I can't send any commands.
什么指令都发不出去了
Send someone to chase.
派人追啊
What are you talking about?
还废什么话
She seems to be
她好像
flying the last ship.
驾驶的是最后一艘船
All of this
这一切
It's not because you don't have the cunning
不是因为您没有城府
The target ship yaws by 0.08.
目标飞船偏航0.08。
but because
而是因为
you are too arrogant.
您太傲慢了
However..
不过
Lord does not care.
主不在乎
B436 base.
B436基地
In the desert by the road.
公路边的荒漠
Throw it out.
扔出去
That button
那个按钮
you
您
forced her to throw away.
逼她扔了
Cheer up Mr. Tyler
振作点儿泰勒先生
Anyway, your experiments
反正以后没有实验了
don't need her anymore.
您不需要她了
Or
或者说
you never needed her.
您从没需要过她
Staff please note.
工作人员请注意
The N31 capsule returning to the surface.
返回地表的N31运载舱
Arriving at the first ring track platform.
即将抵达一环轨道站台
Please go to the platform to prepare for boarding.
请对应班组人员前往站台准备登舱
The inspection of the E ring road is almost finished, no problem.
对E环道快检查完了没问题
Batch D3421 has been inspected, don't worry.
D3421批次已经审验了放心吧
I know I'm unreliable in your eyes
我知道我在你眼里特不靠谱
but,
但是
I'm sorry.
不好意思啊
there is something I must give you
有样东西我一定要给你
accept it or not.
接不接受都行
I was afraid of letting you go.
我是怕这么让你走了
and I would regret it forever.
我会后悔一辈子
No
不用了
you have given me enough.
您给我的已经够多了
Zhuang Yan.
庄颜
No
不
Nothing else.
其他的不算什么
But
但是
But this
但是这个
I
我
Alert.
警报
Damaged solar cell wings.
太阳电池翼损毁
Insufficient power supply.
电源功率不足
Ladder track position deviation increased.
天梯轨位偏差增大
Alert.
警报
What happened?
怎么回事
Well No. 1 in Gaokong First Ring was hit.
高空一环1号井受到撞击
Run fast.
快跑
The outer wall structure of cabin D has broken down.
d舱段外壁结构被击穿
Chief dispatcher.
调度长
Both the solar cell wing and the ring were hit.
太阳电池翼和一环都被撞击了
Another alert.
另帆慌
The 1D compartment of the first ring has broken down.
一环1d舱段被击穿
Gravity Port 2 has a flammable warehouse.
2号重力港有易燃物仓库
Call for emergency assistance on nearby ring roads.
请求附近环道紧急援助
The second ring dispatch received.
二环调度收到
I'm going to call someone.
我去叫人
Is the fiber optic terminal damaged?
光纤终端受损了吗
Can't send anything.
什么都发不出去
Central Axis Rail Station Emergency Lock.
中轴轨道站紧急锁定
All cabins are out of service.
运载舱全部停运
Dull assembly.
全员集合
Check Exoskeleton Status.
检查外骨骼状态
Enable visual enhancements.
启用视觉增强
Locate the damaged point at any time.
随时定位破损点
Hurry up.
快点
Keep up.
快跟上
Axial control center damage.
中轴控制中枢受损
Counterweight adjustment procedure aborted.
配重调节程序中止
Ask the second-level engineer to repair immediately.
请二级工程师立即抢修
I'm chief dispatcher Scott.
我是一环调度长斯科特
I ask everyone in the ring to perform an emergency evacuation.
我要求一环所有人执行紧急撤离
The first-level emergency response plan has been activated.
一级应急处置预案已启用
All emergency shelters and escape pods are open.
所有应急避难所和逃逸舱已开放
Emergency exit blocked
安全出口堵住了
Repeat.
重复
Run everyone.
一环所有人
It's too late to evacuate, help!
来不及撤离了救命啊
Follow the evacuation signs.
沿疏散指示标志
perform an emergency evacuation.
执行紧急撤离
How are you?
你还好吗
Are you injured?
有没有受伤
And you?
你呢
I'm fine.
我没事
What's going on here?
这是怎么了
What happened?
发生什么事了
Can you get up?
起得来吗
Let's get out of here.
我们先离开这
Grab the safety rope.
抓安全绳
Help.
救命啊
Alert.
警报
Damage to the main structure of the No. 2 Gravity Port in Gaokong Yihuan was detected.
检测到高空一环2号重力港主结构损毁
Severe loss of pressure in part of the first ring.
一环部分环道重度失压
All lanes will be closed.
全舱道即将封闭
Warning all cabins are about to be closed.
警报全舱道即将封闭
All personnel on High-altitude First Ring Road G Ring Road H Ring Road.
高空一环G环道H环道所有人员
Immediately evacuate toward the I Ring.
立即向I环道方向撤离
Alert.
警报
The main structure of the No. 2 gravity port in the high-altitude ring is damaged.
高空一环2号重力港主结构损毁
Loss of temperature and pressure in the F ring.
F环道失温失压
Shelter ahead.
避难所在前面
There is a major security risk.
存在重大安全风险
It's going to be sealed.
要封舱啦
All personnel on the E ring road and the F ring road should not stay
E环道F环道所有人员请勿停留
Don't leave me.
别丢下我
Evacuate immediately towards Ring D.
立即向D环道方向撤离
All cabins are being closed.
全舱道正在封闭
There are wounded rescuers.
有伤员救人啊
In the process of sealing.
避险过程中
Beware of stepping on and squeezing the hatch.
谨防踩踏与舱门挤压
What's going on over there?
那边怎么了
Don't stand still, run.
别愣着快跑
Alert.
警报
Get out of the way.
别挡路
The main structure of the No. 2 gravity port in the high-altitude ring is damaged.
高空一环2号重力港主结构损毁
Don't come back here.
别往那边回来
Loss of temperature and pressure in the F ring.
F环道失温失压
There is a major security risk.
存在重大安全风险
All personnel on the E ring road and the F ring road should not stay.
E环道F环道所有人员请勿停留
Why are you standing there? Run away!
愣着干吗快跑啊
where is the shelter?
避难所在哪
It's in front.
是在前面
Alert.
警报
People who have been enclosed in the E ring road F ring road.
已封闭在E环道F环道内的人员
Run fast!
快跑
Walk.
走
Start self-help and mutual aid now.
立即开展自救互助
Get nearby emergency supplies.
就近获取储备应急物资
Open the door.
开门啊
Let's go.
让我们过去
Beware of hypothermia and hypoxia.
谨防失温缺氧
Run fast!
快跑
Those trapped please keep calm.
被困人员请保持冷静
Front door fast.
前面的门快
Patiently waiting for help.
耐心等待救援
Run fast
快跑
Quick
快
Bow your head
低头
Go in.
快进去
Luo Ji.
罗辑
Don't close the door
别关门啊
Alert.
酶土 =r—1
All emergency shelters on B,C D Ring Road are open.
BC D环道应急避难所已全部开放
Open the door.
开门
The escape pods are all unlocked.
逃逸舱已全部解锁
Step aside.
让开
All personnel evacuate quickly.
所有人员迅速避险
Orderly evacuation.
有序撤离
Open the door.
开门
Warning that the high-altitude ring gravity system is about to be paralyzed.
警告 高空一环重力系统即将瘫痪
All personnel are ready for weightlessness and anti-collision.
所有人员做好失重防冲撞准备
The explosion of the truss of the high-altitude station was monitored.
监控到高空站桁架爆炸
All communication is cut off.
通讯全部断了
What about the data of the aerospace measurement and control network?
航天测控网的数据呢
Call them all out.
赶紧都调出来
Ladder track position deviation increased.
天梯轨位偏差增大
Find a space-based observing system.
找天基观测系统
I want more accurate track data.
我要更准确的轨道数据
Chairman.
主席
The sky ladder high-altitude station was hit.
天梯高空站被击中
The situation is very serious.
情况比较严重
Alright.
好了
what do you want to say
你要说什么
The wallbreaker website has revealed Mr. Tyler's plans.
破壁网站公布了泰勒先生的计划
Millions of words.
有上百万字
So quickly.
这么快
Block the messages.
封锁消息
Go to the flight control center now.
立刻去飞控中心
Acknowledged.
收到
Get in touch with Mr. Tyler's lab as soon as possible.
尽快和泰勒先生的实验基地联系
Clear.
明白
The second team is about to arrive at the traffic hall.
二队即将抵达交通大厅
Those with extravehicular tools go first.
带舱外工具的先走
Gas composition analysis.
还有气体组份分析仪
Understood.
收到
Quick.
快
Send it to the professor.
发给博士
We need to get to the flight control center immediately
我们得马上赶到飞控中心
Sign here qickly.
赶紧签
I have to get to the next one.
我去下一家
Pay on delivery.
还到付
Yeah.
对对对
Hurry up.
赶紧的
Do you want something?
你东西还要不要
I'll leave it here.
那我放这了
Automatic debit.
自动扣款
Buckle up.
扣吧
Don’t worry.
别担心
The data inside
里面的数据
was fully recovered.
我们完全复原了
Just as I thought.
和我想的一样
Your judgment is basically accurate.
您的判断基本准确
I mean how how I think
我是说你们切得
you cut this
和我想的
so cleanly.
一样干净
I remember when I was in Daxinganling
记得在大兴安岭的时候
It is like the trees that were cut down
那些被砍掉的树桩子也是这样
but the fracture was much rougher.
但断口粗糙多了
Seems like flying blade is pretty powerful.
看来飞刃挺厉害的
Your solar system defense system
你们的太阳系防御系统
Is it ready to be built?
是准备拿它建吧
Don't ask her how she knows.
不用问她怎么知道
Last question.
最后一个问题
No more questions.
没别的意思
Just let me remind you.
就是想提醒你们
Humans can't control the power they have
人类没法掌握自己拥有的力量
in the face of madness.
在疯狂面前
Reasoning
理智
is weak.
都是软弱无力的
This
这
Isn't it just an example?
不就是例子吗
you
您
do you have any wishes?
还有什么愿望吗
Such a pity
可惜啊
My time
我的时间
is running out.
不多了
Don't worry
不用担心
Your application to return to Red Coast
您回红岸的申请
has been approved.
联大已经批准了
Thank you.
谢谢
or
或者
Do you still want to visit your daughter's grave?
您还想去女儿墓前看看吗
What I want to tell him
我要对他说的
is that it's over.
已经说完了
Take care
那您保重
Professor Ye.
叶教授
I lit the fire
我点燃了火
but can't control it.
却控制不了它
The fire started to spread
火势开始蔓延了
I did what I could.
我也做了我能做的
Now
现在
It's your turn.
该你们了
Although for them a few light-years away
虽然对几光年外的它们来说
It doesn't make sense.
一切都没有意义
But for me
但对我来说
it is meaningful.
是有意义的
We can only choose whether to sacrifice
我们只能选择是否牺牲
but can't choose what to sacrifice.
但不能选择牺牲什么
Mr. Tyler
泰勒先生
We support you.
我们支持你
President says..
萨伊主席